<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Strange and wonderful news from Linconshire [sic], or, A dreadful account of a most inhumane and bloody murther committed upon the body of one Mr. Carter, by the contrivance of his elder brother, who had soon after found out, by the appearance of a most dreadful and terrible ghost, sent by Almighty Providence for the discovery as also, the manner of its appearance in several shapes and forms, with fresh bleeding wounds, still pursuing the murtherer from place to place, with the relation how he endeavoured to conjure it down, and of its appearance and declaration of the murtherers, and of the confession of the murderer when apprehended, with many other remarkable circmstances [sic] / this was communicated in a letter to a gentleman of very good quality in London, the truth of which is attested under the hands of George Smith, James Simson and Gregory Wilson, men of good repute and fame, living near Stampford.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5862A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10012</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13772917</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13772917</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101748</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61764)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101748)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 852:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Strange and wonderful news from Linconshire [sic], or, A dreadful account of a most inhumane and bloody murther committed upon the body of one Mr. Carter, by the contrivance of his elder brother, who had soon after found out, by the appearance of a most dreadful and terrible ghost, sent by Almighty Providence for the discovery as also, the manner of its appearance in several shapes and forms, with fresh bleeding wounds, still pursuing the murtherer from place to place, with the relation how he endeavoured to conjure it down, and of its appearance and declaration of the murtherers, and of the confession of the murderer when apprehended, with many other remarkable circmstances [sic] / this was communicated in a letter to a gentleman of very good quality in London, the truth of which is attested under the hands of George Smith, James Simson and Gregory Wilson, men of good repute and fame, living near Stampford.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ghosts --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apparitions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lincolnshire (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101748:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101748:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
            <p>Strange and wonderful News FROM LINCONSHIRE.</p>
            <p>Or a Dreadful ACCOUNT OF A moſt INHUMANE AND Bloody Murther, Committed upon the Body of one Mr. <hi>Carter,</hi> by the contrivance of his Elder Brother, who <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> three more Villains to commit the hor<gap reason="illegible" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> how it was ſoon after found out, by th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a moſt dreadful and terrible Ghoſt, ſent by Alm<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghty Providence for the Diſcovery.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO The Manner of its Appearance in ſeveral Shapes and Forms, with Freſh bleeding wounds, ſtill purſuing the Murtherer from place, to place; with the Relation how he endeavoured to Conjure it down, and of its Appearance and Declaration of the Murtherers, and of the Confeſſion of the Murderer when Apprehended, with many other remarkable Circmſtances.</p>
            <p>This was Communicated in a Letter to a Gentleman of very good Quality in <hi>London,</hi> The truth of which is Atteſted under the hands of <hi>George Smith, James Simſon, and Gregory Wilſon,</hi> Men of good Repute and Fame, Iiving near <hi>Stampford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, in the Year 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101748:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->
            <head>Strange and wonderful News From Lincolnſhire.</head>
            <p>WOnderful are the dictates of Providence, in all there effects, and Heavens juſtice, ſeldom ſleeps when Crimes, like theſe: cry Loud, Almighty vengeance ſlacks not its dread Arme, but by ſome unexpected means purſues the Trembling offender. Ghoſts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal ſhapes; whoſe Midnight formes, Groan out abſconded horrors, are often Inſtrumeutal made, to the diſcoveries of Vilianous Exploits, as may in this fratericid be amplified more open to the World; Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Carter,</hi> near <hi>Stamford</hi> in <hi>Lincolin-ſhire,</hi> dying not many Months ſince, and leaving two Sonsonly (viz) <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Thomas,</hi> (his Wife being formerly deceaſed) and for their maintenance, a conſiderable compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency; as well in Yearly revenue, as other goods, Chattels and Mony, devided between them equally thereby, thinking he had done diſcretly, to hinder all differances: that after his deceaſe might happen, but as the Glow Worme, Light of Humane Reaſon, cannot ſee into futurity, ſo in this his expectation failed, for the Elder, <hi>(viz) William</hi> being by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an extravagant wild temper: and following Lude Aſſociate, was like <hi>Cain,</hi> Tempred to ſhed the Innocent Blood of his Younger Brother, for ſure it is, that ſuch his envy Sprung at, firſt from the diſlike he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of his Vertuous proceeding, as to procure the poſeſſion of what was fallen to his Lot, upon which he laied many Plots and contrivances, to make him away, and then rather becauſe he was but green in Years, and eaſiy to be wrought upon, at laſt he prevailed with him ſo far as to go to the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge:</hi> and there to ſtudy Divinity, this the Youth agreed to, at his more then ordinary imertunity, and it was given out on all Hands, amongſt the Neighbours, the better to Colour the deſign, the time being appointed for his departeur and things made ready, the Elder Brother had hired 3 of his Wicked accomplices, to meet them upon their Journey, in the diſguiſe of high way Men, by ſuch a Wood ſome diſtance from the Town, and that they there ſhould Murder his Brother, for which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101748:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->they were to receive Ten Pounds a piece, this they effected on <hi>Tueſday,</hi> the 14 of this Inſtant <hi>November,</hi> at which Bloody and Villanous deſign, the ſaid <hi>William</hi> was not leaſt Inſtrumental, for when the Ruffians had ſhot the Young Man of from his Horſe, then he run him through, to make a ſore diſpatch, this being done, they bound the ſaid <hi>William</hi> to make the buſineſs more likely and plauſable, and then away they Rid, not long after ſome Gentlemen came by, who were much amazed at ſo ſtrange a diſaſter, to whom the ſaid <hi>William</hi> with a lamentable Voice told them in many diſſembling Circumſtances, telling them that his Brother being fore-moſt they were met by 6 High-way-men, deſireing him to Yield to their Mercy, and not to make any reſiſtance, but he not taking his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, being well Horſed, endeavoured to Ride throw them, but one of them Fireing a Piſtol, ſhot him, and another with his Rapier Run him through, this daubing with untempered Morter; gained not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief with the Gentlemen, but alſo with the whole Countery, Immediately Hew and Cry, was ſent after the Murderers, and the Body decently buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Brother ſhedding many Crocadils Tears at the Funeral: the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Blind the Eyes of Men, but Heaven whoſe narrow ſearching Eyes can never be deceived, thought ſit to bring ſo Vile a deed to Light, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Bloud cried Loud, whereupon there was a certain rumor ſpread about the place, without a known Author, that there had been a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ghoſt ſeen in Mr. <hi>Carters</hi> Yard, the which he ſtrove to Stifle, by threatning the reporters of it, but it proved a Sceen to true, for by the Divine permiſſion, an Airey form aſſumed the ſhape of his departed Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with freſh bleeding Wounds, the which appeared not only to him in dreadful wife, but at laſt to one of the Servants, upon this a ſuddain change was obſerved in him, and a deep Melancholly over-ſpread, no doubt ſtirred up by inward Guilt; and powerful Conſcience: ſting at laſt the Spirit or Airy form Grew ſo importunat (ſeeing the Servants had ſtrict charge not to reveal to any of the Neighbours any ſuch diſturbance) that for two or three Nights together, there was heard moſt dreadful Groanings, and Laments: and ſuch a Lumbering Noiſe, as if the ſtools and Chairs; and all the other Houſe-hold Goods were Tumbling out of doors: the Hogs and Horſes often making an unuſial Noiſe, ſo that it was heard by ſeveral of the Neighbours, upon which the Rumor ſpread freſh, whereupon he thought convenient to remove to another Houſe, ſome diſtance from that being, the which ſtill raiſed ſuſpicion in ſome Jealous Neighbours, all this while the Servants remaining faithful to their Maſter, would by no means diſcloſe what they had ſeen, but make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlight, when they were asked concerning any ſuch Intreague, but this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101748:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 27 -->removal nothing did avail, for ſtill the dreadful Ghoſt perſued, and often changed it ſelf into more fearful formes, as a Bear, a Lion, and the like with Gaſtly countenance, and horrid Eye, oft ſparkling fire, ſometimes ſhril ſhreaks, and ſometimes Hollow Groans were heard, this he at laſt Imparted to Friend of his (but not the cauſe of its appeatance) who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him to get it Conjured down, amongſt the Neighbours ſtill reports went doubtful, ſome ſaid Old Mr. <hi>Carter</hi> had hid monys, and that being not as yet diſcovered, was the cauſe his reſtleſs Soul could find no fixed aboad, but the Murtherer himſelf, knew a more dreadful cauſe, for its appearance, and therefore took his Friends, advice to lay it, if 'twere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, upon which a Man was ſent for that pretended to Aſtroligy, and all things for the dreadful Intreague were prepared, and Midnight ſilence the Hour for its appearance being come, firſt a Small Noiſe was heard and next, the Room wherein they were did ſeem to ſhake, when loe the Image of the murthered Youth appeared on Horſe-Back juſt as he was ſlain, which ſight ſo amazed the Conjurer, that notwithſtanding his Magnanimous art, he did begin to fly the Room, when as the Spirit bid him not to fear, though it was not in his power to lay him, till his blood (in part ſhed by his Brothers hand, and part by three more: whom he Hired, Nameing them diſtinctly) was by Juſtice anſwered for, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhewing his Wounds he vaniſhed, upon this the murderer was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and before a Majeſtrate confeſſed the whole enterprize, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore recited, and thereupon was committed to the County Goal, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Tryal, the other three being fled upon the diſcovery, and are not to be found, this atteſted under the Hands of <hi>George Smith, James Simſon,</hi> and <hi>Gregory Wilſon,</hi> Men of good repute and Fame, living near the place aforeſaid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this we may ſee and admire the power and Juſtice of an Almighty God who alone is dreadful, and to be feared among all the Nations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
